Register of the Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych Records, 1919-1947.
Hoover Institution Archives
- SERIES NO. 738. REFUGEES
  - 1943
    - Countries
      - Europe (Box 549)
        - Spain
          - Persons imprisoned. Includes list (Folder 16)
          - Polish Red Cross, Barcelona. List of welfare recipients (Folder 17)
          - Release from imprisonment. Includes list (Folder 18)
        - Sweden and Scandinavian countries (Folder 19)
      - Middle East (Box 552)
        - Egypt (Folder 1)
        - Iraq
          - Jewish children. Visas and transit (Folder 2)
          - Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare. Budget and Finances. Reports and list of welfare recipients (Folder 3)
        - Palestine
          - General (Folder 4)
          - Budget and finances (Folder 5)
          - Discharged soldiers and military families (Folder 6)
          - Embezzlements (Folder 7)
          - Junacy (Folder 8)
          - Medical assistance (Folder 9)
          - Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare (Folder 10)
          - Veterans compensation (Folder 11)
          - Welfare and other forms of assistance (Folder 12)
      - Soviet Union
        - General
          - Arrests (Folder 13)
          - Deportations, estimates of (Folder 14)
          - "Materialy dot. losu deportowanych do ZSSR obyw. pol. oraz stos. polsko- -sowieckich". Lists of sources (Folder 15)
        - Children
          - General (Folder 16)
          - Ashabad (Folder 17)
          - Jewish children. Evacuation (Folder 18)
          - Romer-Vyshinsky talks (Folder 19)
        - Citizenship (Folder 20)
        - Countries
          - General (Folder 21)
          - Australia and New Zealand (Folder 22)
          - Australian Legation. Parcels
            - Jan.-Aug. (Folder 23)
            - Sept.-Oct. (Folder 24)
            - Nov.-Dec. (Folder 25)
          - Great Britain. Relief transports (Folder 26)
          - India (Box 553)
            - Deliveries (Folder 1)
            - Suspension of purchasing transactions (Folder 2)
          - Iran
            - General (Folder 3)
            - Centralne Biuro Ewidencji Obywateli Polskich na Wschodzie
              - General (Folder 4)
              - Statue (Folder 5)
            - Evacuation
              - General
                - Jan.-Apr. (Folder 6)
                - May-Dec. (Folder 7)
              - Jews (Folder 8)
              - Plans (Folder 9)
              - Talks with Foreign Office (Folder 10)
            - Finances
              - General (Folder 11)
              - British credits (Folder 12)
              - Embezzlements. Investigation (Folder 13)
                - Commission
            - Komitet Patriotow (Folder 14)
            - Medical assistance
              - General (Folder 15)
              - Hospitals (Folder 16)
            - Ministry of Labor and Social Welfare
              - Budget preliminary, finances (Folder 17)
              - Delegates
                - General (Folder 18)
                - Marjanski, Jerzy (Folder 19)
            - Personal files (Folder 1)
            - Press, publications (Folder 2)
            - Refugee camps
              - Ahwaz (Folder 3)
              - Criminal element (Folder 4)
              - Isfahan (Folder 5)
              - Organization of (Folder 6)
              - Reports (Folder 7)
            - Transport Department
              - General
                - General (Folder 8)
                - January (Folder 9)
                - February
                - 1-15 (Folder 10)
                - 16-28 (Folder 11)
                - March (Folder 12)
                - April (Folder 13)
                - May (Folder 14)
                - June (Folder 15)
                - July (Folder 16)
                - August (Folder 17)
                - September (Box 555, Folder 1)
                - October (Folder 2)
                - November (Folder 3)
                - December (Folder 4)
              - Budget (Folder 5)
            - Warehouses
              - Deliveries (Folder 6)
              - Shipments (Folder 7)
              - Stock list
                - Jan.-Feb. (Folder 8)
                - Mar.-Apr. (Folder 9)
                - May-Oct. (Folder 10)
              - Transport charts (Folder 11)
          - Palestine (Folder 12)
          - United States
            - Delivery of relief (Folder 13)
            - Freedman Agency. Embezzlements (Folder 14)
        - Lists (Box 556)
          - Lithuanian deportees
            - List no. 1
              - A-C (Folder 1)
              - D-H (Ch) (Folder 2)
              - I-K (Folder 3)
              - L-N (Folder 4)
              - O-R (Folder 5)
              - S (Folder 6)
              - T-Z (Folder 7)
            - List no. 2 (ca. 300 names) (Folder 8)
            - List no. 3 (ca. 400 names) (Folder 9)
            - List no. 4 (ca. 2,000 names) (Folder 10)
            - List no. 5 (ca. 400 names) (Folder 11)
            - List no. 6 (ca. 10,000 names)
              - Correspondence (Folder 12)
              - List (Folder 13)
          - Polish deportees
            - "Osoby wyewakuowane z ZSRR", Polska Walczaca. Dodatek, April 1942 (10,000 names). Lists
              - Nos. 1-4 (Folder 14)
              - Nos. 6-9 (Folder 15)
              - Nos. 10-13 (Folder 16)
              - Nos. 15-17 (Folder 17)
            - Persons imprisoned and location of imprisonment (ca. 6,000) (Folder 18)
            - "Polacy przebywajacy w Teheranie", Polska Walczaca. Issues
              - Nos. 1-4 (Folder 19)
              - Nos. 30-34 (Folder 20)
              - Nos. 37-51 (Folder 21)
            - Teachers Union in Great Britain. Families (ca. 130 names) (Folder 22)
            - "Wykaz obywateli polskich w wiezieniach sowieckich, marzec-czerwiec 1942". Typescript (1,261 names) (Folder 23)
        - Military families (Box 557)
          - Assistance (Folder 1)
          - Evacuation (Folder 2)
          - List (156 names) (Folder 3)
        - Moscow Embassy
          - General (Folder 4)
          - Anti-soviet propaganda (Folder 5)
          - Australian Legation
            - Relief (Folder 6)
            - Transfer of responsibilities
              - May-June (Folder 7)
              - July-Aug. (Folder 8)
              - Sept.-Dec. (Folder 9)
            - Visas issued. See box no. 558
          - Closing of government welfare agencies (Folder 10)
          - Evacuation of employees and families. List (Folder 11)
          - Government delegates. List (Folder 12)
          - Iran. Lend-lease goods (Folder 13)
          - Press Department (Folder 14)
          - Raczynski, Edward. Note on British talks with Stalin concerning evacuation of Polish refugees (Folder 15)
          - Reports
            - "Lisiewicz, Teodozja: Raport z Kolymy". Typescript (Folder 16)
            - Mezowie zaufania (Folder 17)
            - "Sprawozdanie z organizacji opiekunczej Ambasady R.P. w ZSRR na dzien 16 IV 1943" (Folder 18)
            - "Wykaz rejonow administracyjnych w ZSRR zamieszkalych przez ludnosc polska" (Folder 19)
            - "Wykaz stanu liczebnosci i rozmieszczenia obywateli polskich w ZSSR w/g stanu na dzien 25 IV 1943". Typescript (Folder 20)
          - Romer, Tadeusz (Folder 21)
          - Talks with Soviet officials
            - Freyd-Fomin, March (Folder 22)
            - Freyd-Novikov, January 11 and 25 (Folder 23)
          - Visas issued to Polish citizens by Australian Legation. Card file (Box 558)
        - Nationalities (Box 559)
          - Czecho-Slovaks (Folder 1)
          - Estonians (Folder 2)
          - "Podstawy doktrynalne i prawne sowiec. polityki narodowosc". Mimeograph (Folder 3)
        - Purchase of food and clothing
          - Africa, East (Folder 4)
          - India (Folder 5)
          - Iran (Folder 6)
          - United States (Folder 7)
        - Refugees
          - General (Folder 8)
          - Bank Polski. Families and employees (Folder 9)
          - Government representatives field reports (Folder 10)
          - Medical assistance (Folder 11)
          - Narkomindel, Diplomatic notes to (Folder 12)
          - Prisoners sentenced by Polish courts left behind in Soviet Union (Folder 13)
          - Quakers (Folder 14)
          - Rapoport, Salomon, Case in Soviet court against (Folder 15)
          - Warehouses (Folder 16)
        - Religion. Priests (Folder 17)
        - Romer, Tadeusz. Office file
          - Ambassador
            - Evacuation to Iran (Folder 18)
            - Finances (Folder 19)
          - Minister. Z.P.P., evacuation (Folder 20)
  - 1943-1944
    - Asia. Far East (Folder 21)
    - Zaleski, Maciej (Folder 22)
  - 1944
    - General
      - General (Folder 23)
      - List of folders created by Ministry employees for SERIES NOS. 164, 245, 478, 738, 791 for 1943-44 (Folder 24)
    - Countries
      - Africa. Estimates on number of refugees (Folder 25)
      - Finland (Folder 26)
      - Portugal. Jews (Folder 27)
      - Soviet Union
        - Australian Legation
          - Ambassador, former. Letter to Romer (Folder 28)
          - Correspondence related to persons remaining on Soviet territory
            - March (Folder 29)
            - April 13-23 (Folder 30)
            - May
              - 4-8 (Folder 31)
              - 11-29 (Folder 32)
            - June
              - 1-7 (Folder 33)
              - 12-15 (Folder 34)
              - 16-29 (Folder 35)
            - July (Box 560, Folder 1)
            - Sept.-Oct. (Folder 2)
        - "Compulsory Refuge: A Few Memories". Mimeogr. (Folder 3)
        - "Deportations from Soviet-Occupied Polish Territories". Mimeograph (Folder 4)
        - "Polacy w Zwiazku Sowieckim". Mimeograph (Folder 5)
- SERIES NO. 745b. FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES. PRISONERS OF WAR
  - 1939. Germany. List of POWs camps (Folder 6)
  - 1940
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Belgium (Folder 8)
    - International Red Cross. Parcel recipients list (Folder 9)
    - Netherlands (Folder 10)
    - Polish Red Cross (Folder 11)
    - "Le sort des prisonniers de guerre polonais" by the Centre d'Information et de Documentation. Mimeograph (Folder 12)
- SERIES NO. 755. POLISH ARMY ABROAD
  - 1937. Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych. "Badanie i ocena fizycznych i psychicznych zdolnosci do sluzby wojskowej podoficerow i szeregowych wykonujacych powszechny obowiazek wojskowy". Mimeograph (Folder 13)
  - 1940
    - General
      - Military Families Bureau
        - Budget preliminary for 1941 (Folder 14)
        - Evacuation of individuals and groups
          - July-Sept. (Folder 15)
          - October (Folder 16)
          - Nov.-Dec. (Folder 17)
        - Personal files
          - A-J (Folder 18)
          - K-M (Folder 19)
          - P-S (Folder 20)
          - T-Z (Folder 21)
      - Countries
        - Africa, North (Folder 22)
        - America, Latin (Folder 23)
        - Australia (Folder 24)
        - Baltic states. Evacuation of Polish soldiers (Folder 25)
        - Canada. Recruitment (Box 561, Folder 1)
        - China (Folder 2)
        - Egypt (Folder 3)
        - Finland (Folder 4)
        - France
          - Demobilization and evacuation
            - July (Folder 5)
            - August (Folder 6)
            - Sept.-Nov. (Folder 7)
          - Military families. List (Folder 8)
          - "Wskazowki dla przybywajacych", April. Flier (Folder 9)
        - Great Britain
          - General (Folder 10)
          - Anglo-Polish military agreement (Folder 11)
          - Military service of Polish nationals (Folder 12)
          - Service registration card (Folder 13)
        - Greece and Balkan states (Folder 14)
        - Hungary (Folder 15)
        - Norway (Folder 16)
        - Portugal. Evacuation (Folder 17)
        - Romania (Folder 18)
        - Spain
          - Evacuation (Folder 19)
          - Internment (Folder 20)
          - Telegrams to Ministry (Folder 21)
        - Sweden (Folder 22)
        - United States
          - General (Folder 23)
          - "Wojsko Polskie w Ameryce: Referat dla Naczelnego Wodza". Typescript (Folder 24)
        - Yugoslavia (Folder 25)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 562)
    - Palestine. Polish army brigade
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Bader, Karol. Reports (Folder 2)
      - Polish involvement in war against Italy (Folder 3)
    - Switzerland. 2nd Division
      - General (Folder 4)
      - Costs of internment (Folder 5)
      - Demobilization (Folder 6)
      - Education (Folder 7)
      - Legal status of Polish soldiers (Folder 8)
      - Winter supplies (Folder 9)
  - 1941
    - General
      - Military courts (Folder 10)
      - Military Families Bureau
        - Annual report (Folder 11)
        - Evacuation (Folder 12)
      - Personal files
        - A-F (Folder 13)
        - G-I (Folder 14)
        - K-L (Folder 15)
        - M-P (Folder 16)
        - R-S (Folder 17)
        - T-Z (Folder 18)
      - "Wytyczne dla prowadzenia zaciagu ochotniczego do Armii Polskiej na terenie...". Questionnaire and instructions (Folder 19)
    - Africa (Box 563, Folder 1)
    - Argentina
      - Jan.-June (Folder 2)
      - July-Dec. (Folder 3)
    - America, Latin (Folder 4)
    - Balkan States
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Recruitment (Folder 6)
    - Brazil (Folder 7)
    - Canada
      - Jan.-April (Folder 8)
      - May-Aug. (Folder 9)
      - Sept.-Dec. (Folder 10)
    - China (Folder 11)
    - Egypt (Folder 12)
    - France
      - General (Folder 13)
      - Jan.-April (Folder 14)
      - May-Aug. (Folder 15)
      - Sept.-Dec. (Folder 16)
      - Family list (Folder 17)
    - Great Britain (Box 564)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Correspondence (Folder 2)
      - Clippings (Folder 3)
      - Desertion (Folder 4)
      - Military service (Folder 5)
      - Provision of funds (Folder 6)
    - India (Folder 7)
    - Ireland (Folder 8)
    - Japan (Folder 9)
    - Morocco (Folder 10)
    - Palestine
      - General (Folder 11)
      - Recruitment (Folder 12)
    - Portugal (Folder 13)
    - South Africa (Folder 14)
    - Soviet Union
      - General (Folder 15)
      - Arms and equipment (Folder 16)
      - Army evacuation. American intervention (Folder 17)
      - Evacuation (Folder 18)
      - Foreign press (Folder 19)
      - Great Britain. Attitude of British communists toward Polish army (Folder 20)
      - Legal and political status of Polish army (Folder 21)
      - "Memorandum on the Missing of Polish Soldiers of War, Formerly Interned at Starobielsk, Kozielsk and Ostashkov (Ostaszkow)". Typescript (Folder 22)
      - Military agreement of August 14 (Folder 23)
      - Religion (Folder 24)
      - Romer, Tadeusz. Communiques to soldiers whose families were deported to Soviet Union (Folder 25)
      - Sikorski, Wladyslaw
        - General (Folder 26)
        - Churchill, Winston. Letter to, Oct. 22 (Folder 27)
        - Kot, Stanislaw, "Objazd generala Sikorskiego po polskich obozach w ZSRR", Dec. 19. Typescript (Folder 28)
      - Talks with Soviet officials (Folder 29)
    - Spain
      - Miranda de Ebro concentration camp
        - General
          - General (Folder 30)
          - Aug.-Sept. (Folder 31)
          - October (Folder 32)
          - Nov.-Dec. (Folder 33)
        - Assistance to prisoners (Box 565, Folder 1)
        - Individual cases (Folder 2)
      - Visas (Folder 3)
    - Sweden (Folder 4)
    - United States
      - General (Folder 5)
      - Pilots. Recruitment and training (Folder 6)
      - Press (Folder 7)
      - Recruitment into Polish army (Folder 8)
  - 1942
    - General
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Military families
        - General (Folder 10)
        - Groups (Folder 11)
      - Ministerstwo Spraw Wojskowych
        - Special communique of April 30 (Folder 12)
        - Sztab Naczelnego Wodza. Division of responsibilities (Folder 13)
      - Notifications of death (Folder 14)
      - "Organizacja naczelnych wladz sil zbrojnych i centralnych instytucji wojskowych". Mimeograph (Folder 15)
      - Personal files
        - A-G (Folder 16)
        - I-K (Folder 17)
        - L-R (Box 566, Folder 1)
        - S-Z (Folder 2)
      - Ukrainians in Polish army (Folder 3)
    - Countries
      - Algeria. Colomb-Bechare camp (Folder 4)
      - America, Latin (Folder 5)
      - Argentina (Folder 6)
      - Australia and New Zealand (Folder 7)
      - Canada
        - General (Folder 8)
        - Recruitment (Folder 9)
      - Egypt (Folder 10)
      - France
        - General (Folder 11)
        - Assistance to demobilized soldiers (Folder 12)
      - Great Britain. Military service
        - Air Force, Squadron 101. Congratulatory letter (Folder 13)
        - Allied Powers War Service Bill (Folder 14)
        - Polish nationals (Folder 15)
      - India (Folder 16)
      - Iran (Folder 17)
      - Ireland (Folder 18)
      - Morocco
        - General (Folder 19)
        - Occupation by Allied Forces (Folder 20)
        - Soldiers released from POW camps (Folder 21)
        - Survivors of Laconia (Folder 22)
        - Visas for soldiers (Folder 23)
      - Palestine (Folder 24)
      - South Africa (Box 567, Folder 1)
      - Soviet Union
        - General (Folder 2)
        - Anders, Wladyslaw
          - Correspondence (Folder 3)
          - Stalin, Joseph. Conversation, March 18. Typescript (Folder 4)
          - Telegrams related to (Folder 5)
        - Army evacuation
          - General (Folder 6)
          - Talks
            - British officials (Folder 7)
            - U.S. officials (Folder 8)
        - Citizenship question (Folder 9)
        - Credits for evacuation (Folder 10)
        - Entry visas for Polish officers from Great Britain (Folder 11)
        - Forced labor camps for Poles withdrawn from Red army (Folder 12)
        - Gawlina, Jozef, Bishop. Trip to (Folder 13)
        - Jewish soldiers (Folder 14)
        - Polish army
          - Situation of. Reports (in English and Polish) (Folder 15)
          - Stationing sites (Folder 16)
        - Religion
          - Kucharski, Ks. Szef Duszpasterstwa Cywilnego (Folder 17)
          - Orthodox rites (Folder 18)
        - Sikorski, Wladyslaw (Folder 19)
        - Soviet officials
          - Correspondence and diplomatic notes (Folder 20)
          - Talks (Folder 21)
      - Spain
        - General
          - Jan.-Mar. (Folder 22)
          - Apr.-June (Folder 23)
          - July-Sept. (Folder 24)
          - Oct.-Dec. (Folder 25)
        - Miranda de Ebro concentration camp
          - Assistance to interned soldiers
            - General (Folder 26)
            - Finances (Folder 27)
          - Camp liquidation (Folder 28)
          - Chiefs of staff representation (Folder 29)
          - International Red Cross (Folder 30)
          - Internees personal files (Box 568, Folder 1)
          - Intervention on behalf of internees
            - Argentina (Folder 2)
            - Chile (Folder 3)
            - Great Britain (Folder 4)
            - United States (Folder 5)
            - Uruguay (Folder 6)
            - Vatican (Folder 7)
            - Venezuela (Folder 8)
          - Szydlowski, Adam (Folder 9)
          - Technicians (Folder 10)
          - Visitation by goverment officials (Folder 11)
      - Sweden (Folder 12)
      - Switzerland
        - General (Folder 13)
        - Press (Folder 14)
      - United States
        - Conditions of enlistment and formation of Polish units (Folder 15)
        - Polish units in American army (Folder 16)
  - 1943
    - General
      - General (Folder 17)
      - Military Families Bureau. Report for 1943 (Folder 18)
      - Minorities (Folder 19)
      - Notification of death (Folder 20)
      - Romer, Tadeusz. Secret file
        - General (Folder 21)
        - Home Army (Folder 22)
        - Pro-Soviet elements in Polish army. Berling, Zygmunt (Folder 23)
      - Wykaz czlonkow bylej Armii Polskiej zamordowanych przez Bolszewikow w Katyniu zidentyfikowanych do dnia 1 czerwca 1943. Pamphlet from German sources
        - Copy 1 (Folder 24)
        - Copy 2 (Folder 25)
    - Countries (Box 569)
      - Africa
        - General
          - East (Folder 1)
          - North (Folder 2)
          - South (Folder 3)
        - Polish liaison officers (Folder 4)
      - Argentina (Folder 5)
      - Australia (Folder 6)
      - Canada (Folder 7)
      - France (Folder 8)
      - Great Britain
        - General (Folder 9)
        - Alimonies (Folder 10)
        - Military service of Polish nationals
          - General (Folder 11)
          - Parliamentary debates (Folder 12)
      - Madagascar (Folder 13)
      - Middle East. Discharged officers (Folder 14)
      - Soviet Union. Formation of 2nd Division. Diplomatic note (Folder 15)
      - Spain
        - Diplomatic representation
          - Inspection report (Folder 16)
          - Szumlakowski, M. (Folder 17)
        - Evacuation
          - France (Folder 18)
          - Portuguese visas (Folder 19)
        - Jaraba camp (Folder 20)
        - Miranda de Ebro concentration camp
          - General (Folder 21)
          - Foreign intervention (Folder 22)
          - Liquidation (Folder 23)
          - Lists
            - Prisoners (Folder 24)
            - Released (Folder 25)
          - Parcels and other forms of assistance (Folder 26)
          - Personal files of internees (Folder 27)
          - Vatican (Folder 28)
          - Visas
            - Argentina. Includes list (Folder 29)
            - Chile (Folder 30)
            - Uruguay. Includes list (Folder 31)
        - Transit to England and Africa (Folder 32)
      - Sweden (Box 570, Folder 1)
      - United States
        - American citizens serving in Polish forces (Folder 2)
        - Soldiers' correspondence with Polish Americans (Folder 3)
  - 1943-1944. Switzerland. 2nd Division (Folder 4)
  - 1944
    - General
      - Budget preliminary for 1945. "Preliminarz budzetowy Polskich Sil Zbrojnych na rok 1945". Mimeograph (Folder 5)
      - Ministerstwo Informacji i Dokumentacji. "Spis bylych jencow wojennych w Rosji, ktorzy wedlug zapodan zrodel niemieckich zostali zabici w Lasku Katynskim". Mimeograph ("cahiers" 10-16) (Folder 6)
      - Minorities (Folder 7)
      - Romer, Tadeusz
        - General (Folder 8)
        - Army, Situation in. Reports (Folder 9)
        - Czech agitation in Polish army (Folder 10)
        - Persons suspected of collaboration with Germans in France (Folder 11)
    - Countries
      - Argentina (Folder 12)
      - Belgium (Folder 13)
      - France
        - General (Folder 14)
        - Mobilization of Czech citizens (Folder 15)
        - Polish-French military agreements of 1939-1940 (Folder 16)
        - Utilization of Polish forces on French territory
          - General (Folder 17)
          - Official documents (Folder 18)
      - Great Britain (Folder 19)
      - India. Kowalski, Antoni (Folder 20)
      - Italy (Folder 21)
      - Palestine
        - General (Folder 22)
        - Latrum internment camp (Folder 23)
      - South Africa (Folder 24)
      - Soviet Union. Katyn massacre
        - Press (Folder 25)
        - Soviet Investigation Commission. "Statement of the Special Commission to Establish and Investigate the Circumstances of the Shooting by German Fascist Invaders of Captive Polish Officers in the Katyn Woods". Mimeograph (translation from Soviet press) (Folder 26)
      - Sweden (Folder 27)
  - 1945
    - Argentina (Folder 28)
    - Palestine. Latrum internment camp (Folder 29)
- SERIES NO. 761. INFORMATION RELATED TO NATIONAL SECURITY
  - 1940. Ministry of Foreign Affairs Office (Box 571, Folder 1)
  - 1941-1942. Persons under suspicion (Folder 2)
  - 1943. Issuance of false passports (Folder 3)
  - 1945. France
    - General (Folder 4)
    - Persons under suspicion (Folder 5)
- SERIES NO. 761f. NATIONAL SECURITY. LITHUANIAN MOVEMENT
  - 1941. Clippings (Folder 6)
  - 1942. National Council's decree on Polish-Soviet relations and on Lithuania (Folder 7)